YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series V. Program Subjects
Sophia Smith Collection
The area in which the place of Christianity in the YWCA was most explicitly identified was in the so-called "Purpose" of the organization as laid out in the organization's Constitution. The Christian Purpose shifted significantly with the changes in the YWCA's programming emphases, membership, and historical context. National Convention action determined changes in Purpose. The membership first adopted a straightforward and adamantly Christian vision of the association's intentions in 1915. They prefaced their Constitution with: "Affirming the Christian faith in God, the Father; and in Jesus Christ, His only Son, our Lord and Savior; and in the Holy Spirit, the Revealer of Truth and Source of Power for Life and Service; according to the teaching of Holy Scripture and the witness of the Church, we adopt the following Constitution." Outlining the function of the YWCA, the Constitution declared that the national YWCA it sought to unite and develop community associations as well as "to advance the physical, social, intellectual, moral, and spiritual interests of young women." Its "ultimate purpose" was "to seek to bring young women to such a knowledge of Jesus Christ as Savior and Lord as shall mean for the individual young woman fullness of life and development of character, and shall make the organization as a whole an effective agency in the bringing in of the Kingdom of God among young women." (Constitution, 1915)
The language of revivalism and of an individual experience of Christ indicated the YWCA's roots in turn-of-the-century evangelism. It held onto this language in the Constitution well after the years of disillusionment that followed the First World War made such sentiments suspect. It took the Second World War and the intention to promulgate a more focused, action-oriented vision of the work of the National Board to inspire a change, and they reached to Christianity as undergirding that focus. In 1949, the organization's purpose read that it was committed to building "a fellowship of women and girls devoted to the task of realizing in our common life those ideals of personal and social living to which we are committed by our faith as Christians. In this endeavor we seek to understand Jesus, to share his love for all people, and to grow in the knowledge and love of God."
The more generalized Christianity evident in the 1949 Constitution depended on a liberal, ecumenical interpretation of the social ethics of Jesus and eschewed references to the millennialism that characterized the older Christian Purpose. This shift aligned with the YWCA's broadened commitment to political and social change and the increasing marginality of their religious programming the at mid-century. Another shift in the Purpose responded to the heated atmosphere of the mid-1960s that heightened the YWCA's commitment to social change. In the 1967 Constitution, the YWCA declared that it was "rooted in the Christian faith as known in Jesus and nourished by the resources of that faith" and called upon its membership to "respond to the barrier-breaking love of God in this day," a goad to activism as necessitated by Christian ethics. The Purpose went on to state that the "Association draws together into responsible membership women and girls of diverse experiences and faiths, that their lives may be open to new understanding and deeper relationships and that together they may join in the struggle for peace and justice, freedom and dignity for all people." The centrality of Christianity to this statement had likely been the result of the reinvigorated sense of Christian Purpose that came out of Commission to the Study the YWCA as a Christian Movement (1964-67), but it belied the ebb of the YWCA as an organization with identifiably Christian programming. Additionally, the YWCA's participation in the civil rights movement, emblematized in many respects by the work of Dorothy Height and her place in the church-based leadership of the movement of the 1950s and early 1960s, gave a certain cachet to a Christian purpose when it was oriented toward the liberal or even radical demand for social equality. The purpose laid out in the 1967 Constitution held until 1988 when the addition of the statement that the "Association will thrust its collective power toward the elimination of racism wherever it exists and by any means necessary" (Constitution, 1988) affirmed decisively the "One Imperative" as fundamental to the organization's mission. In 1992, a revised mission statement again affirmed its roots in Christianity while appealing across lines of faith: "The Young Women's Christian Association of the United States of America is a women's membership movement nourished by its roots in the Christian faith and sustained by the richness of many beliefs and values. Strengthened by diversity, the Association draws together members who strive to create opportunities for women's growth, leadership and power in order to attain a common vision: Peace, justice, freedom and dignity for all people. The Association will thrust its collective power toward the elimination of racism wherever it exists and by any means necessary." (1992 Constitution). This most recent revision stands with its reference to Christianity as part of the living purpose of the YWCA.
Administrative History
1912-22 Department of Method
1923-31 Education and Research
1932-39 Laboratory Division and National Services Division
1940-48 Community Division, Program
1951 Membership Resources, Training Services
1959-84 Leadership Services, Bureau of Research, Studies, and Program Resources
Scope and Content
The Religion Subseries does not contain a comprehensive set of materials on religious matters but contains much of the work carried out under explicitly religious auspices. It best documents the religious publications produced by the national YWCA as it sought to serve the needs of its constituencies and also as it made innovative interpretations of matters of spirituality and religious pedagogy. Many of these publications were authored by YWCA staff. The Woman's Press frequently published works of bible study, prayer, and worship services as well as broader examinations of the place of spirituality and religion in the cultural landscape of twentieth-century America.
The Subseries contains the records of religious committee work, which traces the National Board's efforts to provide programming and meet educational needs for religion in the 1930s and 1940s. Documentation of later committee work is scant but suggestive of the expansive ways in which the organization understood and wished to promulgate its spiritual foundation. In addition, there are a variety of reference materials including studies conducted on the YWCA's religious work as well as more general publications on religious matters that affected the YWCA.
Researchers interested in the YWCA's religious work, particularly of the 1910s through the 1940s, are encouraged to augment the materials in this series with the reports of secretaries of religious matters, which are filed in the Departments of Method and Education and Research. These reports offer detail in the variety of local religious work undertaken, the design of the National Board's religious training of YWCA women, and the evolution of its religious stance. The records of the Foreign Division may convey the YWCA's religious ethos most plainly, as the YWCA was compelled to clarify and make plain its intentions in these missionary and cross-national settings. The shifting course of this religious outlook is also evident in convention proceedings, which scrutinized the place of religion in the organization. The microfilmed religion subject files contain several documents and reports not available in this series; of particular interest are reports from the 1920s studying the problems with Catholic participation in the YWCA.
In later years, religious matters served as a subject of inquiry less frequently. An exception to this was the 1964-67 Commission to Study the YWCA as a Christian Movement. While this Subseries contains the reports that resulted from this Commission, a more comprehensive set of documents is found with Mission/Purpose materials in the General Administration series ( SERIES I in RECORD GROUP 3). A final word would be that religious subjects and work were diffused throughout the organization and, particularly in the early years, touched on nearly all of the YWCA's concerns. Researchers may wish to consult other areas of programming and administration to gain a full picture of the place of religion in the YWCA.
Microfilmed Records, 1884-1970 only
[see Microfilmed Records Reel list]
Records relating to religion in the YWCA can be found on the microfilm under:
Minutes and Reports
New Society and Its Christian Basis Committee
Religion Committee [committees with various names filed together]
Subject Files
National Board, Program Planning Study, Religion
O.O. [Outside Organizations]--Religious
Religion
YWCA-Commission to Study the YWCA as a Christian Movement
Original Format Records, 1907-91, n.d., 5 linear feet
[see Original Format Records Folder list]
The bulk of the original format records consists of publications and resource materials, some of which were microfilmed, though many were not. The rest of the records in this subseries are quite scattered and most of what dates prior to 1970 is probably on the microfilm, including the Committee and Commission records which were not discarded after filming. The small amount of records that post-date the microfilm are primarily about the examinations of the YWCA's Christian Purpose.
The original Format Records are organized as follows:
General and Historical: the YWCA as a Christian organization
Committees and Commissions
Organizations
Reference material
Publications and resource materials (arranged alphabetically)
General
About the YWCA's religious work
Biblical study and exigesis
Prayers and hymns
Worship services
Related Materials
In other Series in this Record Group
Reports of Religious Work secretaries are in the minutes and reports in SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES.
Records of the National Training School in SERIES II. TRAINING AND PERSONNEL contain information about religious training.
In other Record Groups
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY, SERIES I. GENERAL has copies of the YWCA Constitution and records related to amendments to it and to the Purpose reflecting the changing religious emphasis within the Association. SERIES III. MEMBERSHIP OF INDIVIDUALS has information about religious affiliation and membership requirements.
See RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES for Convention deliberations about the role of religion in membership issues and the Purpose of the Association.
See RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK for information about the "interpretation" of Christianity in other countries and its reception there.
Concern over college students' tendency to abandon religion led the National Association to pay particular attention to the content of and methods for engaging college students in deeper thinking about religion. This concern is reflected in the records of the Student Work in RECORD GROUP 7.
The YWCA made videotapes of various presentations and panels related to the 1989-90 re-examination of the Purpose. These are in RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
Camps Administration; Camps for girls; Drama--United States--History--20th century; Health education of women--United States--History--Sources; Hygiene, Sexual--History--20th century--Sources; Marriage, Companionate--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Nature Study; Physical education for women--History--20th century--Sources; Physical fitness for women--History--20th century; Religion--Study and teaching--History--Sources; Sex instruction--United States--History--Sources; Spirituality--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women and religion--History--Sources; Women--Health and hygiene--United States--20th century; Women in Christianity--United States--History--Sources
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES
SERIES II. TRAINING AND PERSONNEL
SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY
SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS
SERIES V. PROGRAM SUBJECTS
SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS
SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
- SERIES V. PROGRAM SUBJECTS
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Scope and Content note for more description.
  - Subseries A. Camping and Outdoor Recreation
    - General and History
      - General, 1919-90, n.d. (Box 585, Folder 1-2)
      - "A Survey of the program of activities and related factors in seventy-one YWCA summer resident camps," by Tonia Seiberlich, Boston University School of Education masters thesis, 1961 (Box 585, Folder 3)
      - "A Study of YWCA Camping Programs to Determine What Services the National Board, YWCA Should Offer Local Associations on a Continuing Basis," by Elizabeth Boyd, New York University School of Social Work masters thesis, circa 1965 (Box 585, Folder 4)
      - Camping Workshop, Atlanta, Georgia, Oct 1968 (Box 585, Folder 5)
      - Reference materials, 1948, 1964, n.d. (Box 585, Folder 6)
    - Minutes and Reports
      - Camp Department, Business Division, 1922-23 (Box 585, Folder 7)
      - Camp Commission (technical and economic), 1924 (Box 585, Folder 8)
      - Camp Commission (Commission to Study the Function of Camps Owned by the National Board), 1925-26 (Box 585, Folder 9)
      - Regional
        - Delaware, Maryland and Pennsylvania/East Central Field (Nepawhin and Canadohta), 1912-19 (Box 585, Folder 10-11)
        - North Central Field (Okoboji), 1920-21 (Box 585, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence
      - American Camping Association, 1948, 1968-71 (Box 585, Folder 13-14)
      - Central Region
        - General, 1961-71, n.d. (Box 585, Folder 15)
        - Camp Bide-A-Wee (Wichita YWCA), 1968-69 (Box 585, Folder 16)
      - Eastern Region
        - General, 1955-69, n.d. (Box 585, Folder 17)
        - Buffalo YWCA, 1968-71 (Box 585, Folder 18)
        - Camp Blazing Trail (Boston YWCA), 1967-69 (Box 586, Folder 1)
      - Southern Region, 1966-70, n.d. (Box 586, Folder 2)
      - Western Region
        - General, 1966-68, n.d. (Box 586, Folder 3)
        - Camp Timbertall (San Francisco Bay Area YWCAs), 1965-69 (Box 586, Folder 4)
        - Tahquitz Meadows (YWCA Camping Council of Southern California), 1960-68 (Box 586, Folder 5)
    - Conferences
      - American Camping Association Convention: YWCA Kindred Group Meeting, 1964 (Box 586, Folder 6)
      - National YWCA Conference on Outdoor Recreation and Conservation, 1964
        - Planning and correspondence, 1962-65, n.d. (Box 586, Folder 7-8)
        - Press releases and news clippings, 1964 (Box 586, Folder 9)
        - Program, 1964 (Box 586, Folder 10)
        - Reports, 1964-66 (Box 586, Folder 11)
      - Second National YWCA Conference on Outdoor Recreation and Conservation, 1966, [see also Y-teen pilot work camp below]
        - General (Box 586, Folder 12)
        - Speeches (Box 586, Folder 13)
        - Reference materials re National Parks and Grand Teton area (Box 586, Folder 14)
    - Programs
      - International Camper Exchange Program, 1966-69, n.d. (Box 586, Folder 15-16)
      - Y-Teen Pilot Work Camp (Gros Ventre Slide, Teton National Forest, Wyoming),9-23 Jul 1966
        - Planning, 1964-66 (Box 586, Folder 17)
        - Correspondence, 1965-69 (Box 586, Folder 18)
        - Leadership, 1965-66 (Box 587, Folder 1)
        - Newspaper clippings and press releases, 1966 (Box 587, Folder 2)
        - Reports, 1966, n.d. (Box 587, Folder 3)
        - Scrapbook (disassembled), 1966 (Box 587, Folder 4)
        - Film "Aim, Action, Achievement"
          - General, 1967-68 (Box 587, Folder 5)
          - White House premiere, 1968 (Box 587, Folder 6)
        - Follow-up, 1966-67 (Box 587, Folder 7)
    - Publications
      - "A Selected Bibliography for YWCA Camp Leadership," 1967 (Box 587, Folder 8)
      - Camping With Purpose by Marie Lafferty Cortell, 1950 (Box 587, Folder 9)
      - Camps and Their Modern Administration by Hazel K. Allen, 1930 (Box 587, Folder 10)
      - Community Action for Outdoor Recreation and Conservation, 1965 (Box 587, Folder 11)
      - County Summer Camps of the YWCA, 1918 (Box 587, Folder 12)
      - "Day Camp: Work Sheets for the Planning of Day Camp," 1944 (Box 587, Folder 13)
      - Explorers: A Camp Project by Marion Dudley and Exploring the Pathways to God: Services of Worship for Use in a Summer Camp by Edith Cousins, 1926 (Box 587, Folder 14)
      - The Girls' Camp by Abbie Graham, 1933 (Box 587, Folder 15)
      - Magic Casements: The Chronicle of the Development of a New Kind of Camp Program by Ruth Perkins, 1927 (Box 587, Folder 16)
      - Nature Study pamphlets: no. 1 "Nature in Camp: Flowers, Ferns, Trees, Stars, Birds, Insects," no. 2 "The Sky: Winter Nights," no. 3 "A Trip to the Moon," no. 4 "All Night With the Stars," no. 5 "The Sky: Spring and Summer Nights" by Louise Brown, 1920 (Box 588, Folder 1)
      - "Outdoor Activities" by Blanche Bogert and Edith M. Gates, 1933, 1942 (Box 588, Folder 2)
      - Working at Play in Summer Camps by Abbie Graham, 1941 (Box 588, Folder 3)
    - Reference materials, 1930-56 (Box 588, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Records of the camp at the Archie Allen Place, Port Byron, Illinois, used by the YWCA of Rock Island, Illinois, among other organizations, 1922-50, n.d. (Box 589, Folder 1-4)
      - Field and Camp Notebook, Comstock Publishing Co., circa 1928 used by Frances W. Kinkead (?) at Camp Maqua, Poland, Maine (Box 589, Folder 5)
      - Port Richey Camp, Pinellas County, Florida: scrapbook, 1925, [photocopy] (Box 589, Folder 6)
      - Camp Rest-a-While, Cloudcroft, New Mexico: camp logs, 1939, 1941 (Box 590, Folder 1-2)
      - Camp Scrap Book, Polly Lee, 1926-34: Camp Chelan, Sellersburg, IN, 1927-28; Camp Daniel Boone, Valley View, KY; International Older Boys' and Girls' Camp Conferences, Lake Geneva, WI 1929, 1934 (Box 590, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B. Health and Recreation
    - General and History
      - General, 1890-1996, n.d. (Box 591, Folder 1-4)
      - "History of the Health Education Movement in the YWCA," 1930 (Box 591, Folder 5)
      - "The YWCA Program of Recreation and Health, Studied with Reference to Problems Reflecting the War Situation" Wellesley College Department of Hygiene and Physical Education graduate seminar report by Maxine Shurtz, 1943 (Box 591, Folder 6)
      - World YWCA Survey of Health, Physical Education, and Camping Activities, 1971 (Box 591, Folder 7)
      - Administration of Health Education Programs in local YWCAs, n.d. (Box 591, Folder 8)
      - Bibliographies, 1962, n.d. (Box 591, Folder 9)
      - Dancing, 1921, 1932, n.d. (Box 591, Folder 10)
      - Health Education Secretaries: standards and qualifications, 1924-48 (Box 591, Folder 11)
      - Marriage and Family Life, 1924, 1949-66 (Box 591, Folder 12)
      - Medical Examinations
        - General, 1932-60, n.d. (Box 591, Folder 13)
        - Study by Health Education Subcommittee of Community Division Committee, 1946 (Box 591)
          - Notes (Box 591, Folder 14)
          - Questionnaire responses (alphabetical by city), E-Z (Box 591, Folder 15-17)
      - Physical Fitness Tests, 1962-76 (Box 591, Folder 18)
      - Policy on Competitive Sports, 1965-66, n.d. (Box 591, Folder 19)
      - Radio talks by Jane Bellows, 1924 (Box 591, Folder 20)
      - Recreation, circa 1920-22, 1941 (Box 591, Folder 21)
      - Reports
        - Miscellaneous, 1915-57 (Box 591, Folder 22)
        - Commission on Experimentation in Administration of Health Education: interim report, 1938-40 (Box 592, Folder 1)
      - Sex Education (Human Sexuality, Social Morality), 1919-86 (Box 592, Folder 2)
      - Smoking, 1922, 1964-69 (Box 592, Folder 3)
      - Swimming Pools
        - General, 1914, 1970-91 (Box 592, Folder 4)
        - "Investigation about Swimming Pools," 1907 (Box 592, Folder 5)
        - Swimming Pool Safety Audit and Program Survey, Aquatic Consulting Services, 1987 (Box 592, Folder 6)
      - U.S. National Health Policy, 1938, 1949 (Box 592, Folder 7)
    - Committees, Commissions, Offices
      - Social Morality Commission (aka Commission Number Three), 1913-19 (Box 592, Folder 8)
      - Bureau of Social Education
        - Minutes and reports, Mar 1919-Jan 1922 (Box 592, Folder 9)
      - Subcommittee on Health Education, Community Division, 1942-50 (Box 592, Folder 10)
      - Health Education, Program Unit
        - Mailings, 1942-49 (Box 592, Folder 11)
      - Health, Physical Education, and Recreation (HPER), Program Unit
        - Mailings, 1985 (Box 592, Folder 12)
        - Program Approval/Training Approval packet, circa 1984 (Box 592, Folder 13)
      - Health and Sports Advocacy
        - General, 1996-98, n.d. (Box 592, Folder 14-15)
        - Health Promotion and Sport directors lists, 1994-97 (Box 592, Folder 16)
        - Partners in Development consulting trip to YWCA of Belize, 1998-99 (Box 592, Folder 17)
        - Research Report on African-American Women and Exercise, Essence Magazine and YWCA of the USA, 1998-99 (Box 592, Folder 18)
        - United States Olympic Committee, F.L.A.M.E. Program, 1997-99 (Box 592, Folder 19)
      - Office of Women's Health Initiatives, Advocacy and Research Division
        - General, 1995-98 (Box 592, Folder 20)
        - Funding proposal to Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, 1998 (Box 592, Folder 21)
        - Mailings to Women's Health Advocacy Network, 1999-2001 [incomplete] (Box 593, Folder 1-7)
        - Organizations
          - General, 1996-2001 (Box 593, Folder 8)
          - Intercultural Cancer Council, 1995-98 (Box 593, Folder 9-11)
          - Jacobs Institute on Women's Health, 1994-98 (Box 593, Folder 12)
        - Task Force re expansion of office
          - General, 1998 (Box 593, Folder 13)
          - Survey of member associations, 1998 (Box 593, Folder 14)
    - Conferences and Workshops, YWCA
      - Social Education Conference, 1919 (Box 593, Folder 15)